TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
（トロガイ）ハァ…
There wasn't much snow this winter.
今年は雪が少なかったねえ
Ah, I see.
Nyunga Ro lm died, did it?
そうか
ニュンガ･ロ･イムが逝ったか
Episode 23
In Search of the Shigu Salua
（ガカイ）すまん 出立までに
すべてを読み解くことができなかった
I'm sorry. We weren't able to decipher
everything before your departure.
（シュガ）いいえ
皇子を卵食いから守る手だてが―
Not at all. It's enough
that we found a way...
見つけられただけでも十分です
...to protect the prince
from the egg-eater.
That is true.
Even a demon from Nayug...
（ガカイ）そうだな
いかなナユグの魔物とて―
...can be defeated
if struck at its weak point.
弱点を突けば倒せるだろう
（シュガ）ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
（ガカイ）何か新しいことが分かれば
馬を走らせよう
If we uncover anything new,
I shall dispatch a rider to you.
行きたまえ
You should go.
（二ノ妃(にのきさき)）
いよいよ出立なさるのですね
So, the time has finally
come for you to set off.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I shall save Prince Chagum's life...
（シュガ）
はい この命に代えても―
チャグム皇子をお救いいたします
...even if the price
should be my own.
Good luck to you.
（二ノ妃）
よろしく お願いいたします
でも あなたも
生きて帰らなければなりません
However, you must
return safely to us as well.
You have already become
indispensable to this country.
あなたは この国にとって
すでに なくてはならない御仁…
（シュガ）いってまいります
I will take my leave.
（バルサ）
うん？ どうした？ チャグム
What's the matter, Chagum?
Torogai!
（チャグム）トロガイ師
（タンダ）師匠 また そのロバ…
Torogai? You're riding
that donkey again?
Well, it insisted on coming with me.
（トロガイ）どうしても わしと
一緒に行きたいと言うもんでの
うん？ 小僧…
Boy?
ちゃんと
男の顔になってるじゃないか
You're starting to
look like a man, I see.
Well, Chagum is 12 now, after all.
（バルサ）
チャグムも もう12ですから
I had a feeling that
this might happen.
そんなこったろうと思ってな
Here.
そらっ
What's this?
（チャグム）これは？
（トロガイ）いつまでも
子供の服ってわけにもいかんだろう
You can't walk around in
children's clothes forever.
Change into those,
and let's have a look at you!
そいつに着替えてみせな
Come to think of it, Tanda...
そういやタンダも あれぐらいの年から
急に でっかくなってったっけね
...also had a growth spurt
around that age, didn't he?
そうか？
I did?
You sure did. Till then, you
were just my cute little brother.
そうさ それまでは
かわいい弟だったのに
あのとき気付いたもんさ
That's when it occurred to me.
The passage of time
changes all sorts of things.
時の流れは いろんなもんを
変えちまうんだってね
Shoo.
（トロガイ）それ ご苦労だったね
Thanks for your help.
Here, catch. That's what
you asked me to get for you.
そらよ 頼まれてたものだ
ほう
（タンダ）へえ
You weren't a prince
for nothing, I see.
（トロガイ）さすが
元皇子だけのことはあるねえ
Do I look strange?
変かな？
よく似合ってるよ
あんたも立派な若者だね
It looks good on you.
You look like a fine young man now.
This is from me.
これは私からだ
A sword's weight is a life's weight.
“剣の重みは命の重み”
The sword you hold represents
your life as well as your death.
“その剣は そなたの生であり
死である”
Whenever you draw it...
“それを抜くときは 自分の命を
その刃(やいば)に託したものと覚悟せよ”
...do so in the knowledge that you
have entrusted your life to its blade.
It's a saying we have in Kanbal.
カンバルの言葉さ
本当は 一人前になった息子に
短剣を授ける儀式のとき―
It's recited during the
coming-of-age ritual...
...when a son receives
his first short sword.
Of course, the father
is supposed to say it.
父親が言うんだけどね
Thank you, Balsa.
ありがとう バルサ
Chagum, what's the matter?
チャグム どうしたんだ？
I was summoned.
呼ばれた
By whom?
（タンダ）誰に？
It's not a voice.
声じゃない
It's a powerful sensation like I'm being
pulled by a string that I can't see.
目に見えない糸に
引っ張られているような―
強い感じがするんだ
The egg was
whispering to you, I see.
ささやいたんだね 卵が
So, where do you want to go?
で どこへ行きたいんだい？
（トロガイ）
そうか 宴(うたげ)の地ってのは―
Well, well...
So, the land of feasting
is one of the springs...
建国正史(けんこくせいし)にある
青弓(あおゆみ)に流れる泉のどれかだね
...that feed into the Aoyumi
like it said in the official history?
小僧 案内してもらうよ
All right, boy,
show us the way there.
出発しよう
Let's move out.
（トロガイ）
母親みたいな顔しおって
Look at that motherly
expression on your face.
いけませんか？
Is that wrong?
Assuming that you survive all this...
もし 無事
生き延びることができたとして―
...what do you plan
to do afterwards?
お前さん そのあと どうする？
ひとところに
とどまるのも悪くないよ
There's something to be said
for settling down in one place.
子を産んで育てるのも
楽しいもんさ
Having children and raising
them is enjoyable enough.
You make it sound like
you've had children of your own.
子を産んだことがあるような
口ぶりですね？
I've had three of them.
３人 産んだ
What, really?
ホントですか？
そんなことで
うそをついてどうする
Why would I lie about
something like that?
Lately...
最近…
同じ夢を よく見ますよ
Lately, I've had
this recurring dream.
夢？
A dream?
Yes.
どんな夢じゃ？
What sort of dream?
Ah, I see...
そうかい
ねえ タンダ？
Say, Tanda...
Did you ever get an
answer from Balsa?
バルサから
返事 聞かせてもらった？
Answer to what?
返事って？
You know, what you said
to her back at Hunter's Hole.
ほら 前に狩穴で言ってたでしょう
About the three of us
living together.
３人で一緒に暮らす話
You were listening?
聞いてたのか
まいったな
I don't know what to say...
You should just marry her
as soon as you can.
さっさと めとっちゃえばいいのに
Don't make it sound so easy.
簡単に言うなよ
Balsa and I both
have complicated lives.
俺にもバルサにも
いろいろあるんだよ
Are you talking
about Balsa's oath?
それってバルサの誓いのこと？
Well, there's that, but we've
probably spent too much time together.
それもあるけど 多分
長く一緒に居過ぎちまったんだよ
それで だんだん
距離ができちまったっていうかさ
It's like we've gradually
grown farther apart or something.
（タンダ）昔は 夏の日ざしみたいな
燃える思いもあったけど―
In the old days, my feelings for her
were hot like the summer sunshine.
時がたつにつれ 秋の風みたいな
穏やかな思いに変わってきたんだよ
Over the years, though...
...they've changed...
turned warm like the autumn wind.
だから まだ このままでいいんだ
Anyway, that's why I'm fine with
keeping things the way they are.
Are you sure?
そうかなあ？
Look, let's just forget
about this, please.
そのくらいで勘弁してくれよ
No matter how much I mull over it,
this is one thing I can't solve on my own.
こればっかりは
俺１人が いくら考えたって―
どうしようもないことなんだからさ
Then why don't I go
ask Balsa for you?
じゃあ
俺が聞いてみようか？ バルサに
チャグムは どうして
そこまで思い切れるようになったんだ？
When did you get
so decisive, Chagum?
And here I am, scared out of
my wits over just about everything.
俺は いろんなことが
怖くてしかたがないってのに
I realized something.
分かったんだ
もし 自分が死んだとしても―
Even if I die, I know I'll be able to
leave behind a legacy, so it's all right.
必ず何かを残せるから
大丈夫だって
バルサに ジグロの話を
聞かせてもらってから―
Ever since Balsa
told me all about Jiguro...
...I've been able to
look at life that way.
そう思えるようになったんだ
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（モン）短槍(たんそう)使いと
剣を交えてはならぬとは―
We're not to engage the
spear-wielder? I don't follow you, sir.
どういう意味でしょうか？
Our interests coincide with hers.
あの者たちと
利害は一致しているのだ
もはや
刃を向け合う道理はない
There is no longer
any reason to fight her.
In addition, there are Prince
Chagum's feelings to consider.
それに チャグム皇子の思いもある
Understood.
分かりました
（無人の体(てい)１）シュガ様 指示どおり
えりすぐりの弓取り３名を―
Master Shuga.
As per your instructions,
three of our best archers...
帰りの山道に忍ばせました
...have been concealed
on the return trail.
I see.
そうか
（無人の体１）ですが…
本当に よろしいのですか？
But are you sure that's
what you want to do?
We have no choice.
It is what the mikado ordered.
しかたあるまい 帝(みかど)の命(めい)だ
（トロガイ）水が少ない
There isn't much water.
Looks like the first signs of drought
are starting to show themselves.
干ばつの兆候は
出始めているようだね
So, up ahead is the
promised land, eh?
この先が“約束の地”ってわけだ
（タンダ）
ものすごい数のシグ･サルアですね
Look at all those shigu salua flowers.
（トロガイ）青池(あおいけ)？
ここが宴の地なのか？
Aoike? This is
the land of feasting?
I don't know.
分からない
（シュガ）トロガイ師
約束を果たしに来ました
Mistress Torogai, we have come
to fulfill our end of the bargain.
Well, I'm glad to see that
you didn't come empty-handed!
手ぶらじゃなさそうで
安心したよ
チャグム皇太子殿下
Crown Prince Chagum.
We have come to assist
in the birth of the water spirit...
これより
水の精霊の誕生をお助けし―
...and to welcome you back as
the hero who saved Shin-Yogo.
新ヨゴ皇国を救った英雄として
還御(かんぎょ)していただきたく―
お迎えに参りました
Shuga, so my brother is truly...
シュガ やっぱり兄上は…
So, he's "the hero who
saved Yogo" now, is he?
…にしても
ヨゴを救った英雄とは―
That's quite a change
of heart you've had.
ずいぶんと
手のひらを返したもんだね
Female bodyguard,
our interests now coincide.
（シュガ）女用心棒よ
すでに我らの利害は一致している
I realize that we may not
have always seen eye to eye...
何度かの行き違いはあったが―
この者たちが そなたらに
害することは もはやない
...but these men no longer
mean you any harm.
星読み博士よ
Star reader. Your words may sound noble,
but if we now share a common goal...
大層な鼻息だがね
利害が一致していると言うんなら―
ラルンガの退治方法を
さっさと聞かせてもらおうか？
...cut to the chase and
tell us how to kill the Rarunga.
A Rarunga's weakness is fire.
ラルンガの弱点は火です
It was written in the epitaphs
that the Warriors Eight...
“聖祖に従った八武人(はちぶじん)は
火をもってラルンガを退けた”と―
...who served the founding father
drove off the Rarunga using fire.
碑文に記されていました
ほう… なるほど
Now I see! It's a question of
relative strengths between spirits.
そうか 精霊の相克じゃな
水は土に負け 土は火に負ける
Water is beaten by earth,
and earth is beaten by fire.
Rarunga, which devour the egg of the
water spirit...are they earth spirits?
水の精霊の卵を食うラルンガは
土の精霊か！
くそっ こんな単純なことに
気付かなかったとはな
Damn, I can't believe I didn't
make such a simple connection...
Then the torches used in the summer
solstice festival are vestiges of that?
ってことは
夏至祭の大たいまつは その名残か！
（モン）そうだ 200年を経た今―
That's right.
And now, 200 years later,
that duty has once again fallen to us.
その任が
再び 我らに巡ってきたのだ
（バルサ）あんたらは
八武人の末えいってわけだ
So, you are the descendants
of the Warriors Eight.
チャグム？
Chagum?
Chagum!
チャグム！
Incredible!
なんと！
The power of the egg?
卵の力か？
待て！ うかつに動くな
Wait! Don't do anything rash.
Torogai, it was written
that the egg is to be born...
トロガイ師 精霊の誕生は―
...on the night of the spring equinox
when the double moon rises.
春分に二つ月が昇った晩と
記されていました
Nightfall is still far off.
What, then, is causing...
まだ 宵の口すら程遠い
これは一体？
さあな わしも
ここからは どうなるか分からん
No idea. I don't know
what's going to happen either.
一応 警戒しておきな
You'd best be on
your guard, though.
チャグム…
Chagum...
What in the world is he doing?
一体 何をしているんだ？
（ガカイ）違う…
We were wrong...
We were mistaken, Shuga!
違うぞ シュガ！
How can this be?
Why did we learn this only now?
なんたること！ この期に及んで…
残りは何枚だ？
How many tablets are left!
（星読み）恐らく あと８枚
There should be eight remaining.
それを一気に引き上げろ
引き上げ班を呼び戻せ！
Bring them all up in one go!
Go summon the retrieval team!
But, master, we can't make them
dive so many times in a single day.
（星読み）しかし
１日に何度も潜らせるわけには…
Where does your duty lie?
（ガカイ）貴様らの役目は何だ！
Will you read the stars
in a destroyed nation?
滅んだ国で星を読む気か！
Prince Sagum,
grant me your protection...
サグム殿下 我にご加護を
Chagum, are you all right?
（バルサ）チャグム 大丈夫かい？
This sense of malice...
It's not natural.
この殺気 ただごとじゃないね
ナユグのモノか しかし どこだ？
Is it something from Nayug?
But where is it?
あれは！
That's...
卵食い ラルンガか？
Is that a Rarunga?
Is that the egg-eater?
火をつけろ！
Light your weapons!
Take position!
展開！
You people stay back!
（モン）お前たちは下がっていろ！
My senses, they're...
（チャグム）感覚が…
チャグム！
Chagum!
Attack!
突け！
（兵士たち）えいっ！
Is it dead?
やったか？
まだいるぞ！
It's still here!
Chagum?
チャグム？
Chagum!
チャグム！
皇子！
Highness!
小僧のヤツ どこへ行く気だ？
Where does that boy
think he's going?
（星読み）ガカイ様！
Master Gakai!
Shuga, Aoike isn't
the land of feasting...
シュガよ
青池は宴の地ではないぞ
Master Gakai!
ガカイ様！
S-Send these tablets
to Shuga at Aoike!
こ… この石板を青池のシュガに…
シュガなら
じかに読むことができる
He should be able to
decipher them on the spot...
馬を飛ばせば間に合う！
If the messenger rides at top speed,
he'll make it in time!
ガカイ様…
Master Gakai...
（無人の体２）ハッ！
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
～♪
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
Next Time
They have finally made
peace with each other.
However, the missing epitaphs
turn everything on its head.
Next time, "The Last Hope."
Episode 24
The Last Hope
Tanda's courage
keeps their hopes alive.